Guide to the Cass Gilbert Papers and Architectural Drawings 1883-1952 (Bulk 1900-1934) PR 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Project Files
  - Subseries I: Foldered Material
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 27 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 554)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 28 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 555)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 29 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 556)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 30 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 557)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 31 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 558)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 32 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 559)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 33 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 560)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 34 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 561)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 35 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 562)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 36 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 563)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 37 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 564)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 38 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 564-A)
    - Woolworth Building (New York, NY) (Box 39 of 39), 1910-1933 (Offsite-box 565)
    - Woolworth Memorial Church (Great Bend, NY), 1912-1914 (Offsite-box 565)
    - Judge George B. Young Monument (Martha's Vineyard, MA), 1903-1907 (Offsite-box 565)
    - Projects Unclear, 1900-1936 (Offsite-box 565)
  - Subseries II: Bound Volumes
    This subseries contains all the volumes relating to Cass Gilbert's architectural projects. The volumes are mainly letterbooks containing outgoing copies of correspondence or books of specifications. Other volumes include records of contracts or financial ledgers. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1929-1930 (Offsite-box CG-195, Volume 1-3)
    - American Insurance Company Building (1 of 2), 1902-1921 (Offsite-box CG-195, Volume 4-6)
    - American Insurance Company Building (2 of 2), 1902-1921 (Offsite-box CG-196, Volume 7-8)
    - Arkansas State Capitol, 1909-1912 (Offsite-box CG-196, Volume 9-11)
    - Austin Nichols & Company (1 of 2), 1913-1916 (Offsite-box CG-196, Volume 12)
    - Austin Nichols & Company (2 of 2), 1913-1916 (Offsite-box CG-197, Volume 13-16)
    - Beverly Public Library, 1910-1914 (Offsite-box CG-197, Volume 17)
    - Bridgeport Savings Bank (1 of 2), 1916-1929 (Offsite-box CG-197, Volume 18)
    - Bridgeport Savings Bank (2 of 2), 1916-1929 (Offsite-box CG-198, Volume 19-22)
    - Broadway Chambers Building (1 of 2), 1898-1901 (Offsite-box CG-198, Volume 23)
    - Broadway Chambers Building (2 of 2), 1898-1901 (Offsite-box CG-199, Volume 24-26)
    - Chase Manufacturing Company Offices (1 of 2), 1916-1920 (Offsite-box CG-199, Volume 27-28)
    - Chase Manufacturing Company Offices (2 of 2), 1916-1920 (Offsite-box CG-200, Volume 29)
    - Chase Memorial Dispensary, 1923-1924 (Offsite-box CG-200, Volume 30)
    - Detroit Public Library (1 of 2), 1913-1922 (Offsite-box CG-200, Volume 31-33)
    - Detroit Public Library (2 of 2), 1913-1922 (Offsite-box CG-201, Volume 34-36)
    - Essex Country Courthouse (1 of 2), 1901-1907 (Offsite-box CG-201, Volume 37)
    - Essex Country Courthouse (2 of 2), 1901-1907 (Offsite-box CG-202, Volume 38-42)
    - Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (1 of 2), 1921-1925 (Offsite-box CG-202, Volume 43)
    - Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (2 of 2), 1921-1925 (Offsite-box CG-203, Volume 44-46)
    - First Division Memorial, 1924-1935 (Offsite-box CG-203, Volume 47)
    - Floranada Club, 1925-1926 (Offsite-box CG-204, Volume 48)
    - G. Fox and Co. Department Store, 1917 (Offsite-box CG-204, Volume 49-50)
    - Helena Hotel, 1912 (Offsite-box CG-204, Volume 51)
    - Hotchkiss School (1 of 2), 1914-1930 (Offsite-box CG-204, Volume 52)
    - Hotchkiss School (2 of 2), 1914-1930 (Offsite-box CG-205, Volume 53-57)
    - Hudson River Bridge (1 of 3), 1926-1934 (Offsite-box CG-205, Volume 58)
    - Hudson River Bridge (2 of 3), 1926-1934 (Offsite-box CG-206, Volume 59)
    - Hudson River Bridge (3 of 3), 1926-1934 (Offsite-box CG-207, Volume 60)
    - Interzone Building, 1923-1931 (Offsite-box CG-207, Volume 61-64)
    - Ives Memorial Library, 1908-1911 (Offsite-box CG-208, Volume 65-68)
    - James House, 1931-1932 (Offsite-box CG-208, Volume 69)
    - Kill Van Kull Bridge, 1926-1934 (Offsite-box CG-206, Volume 70-71)
    - Kinney Building (1 of 3), 1912-1931 (Offsite-box CG-208, Volume 72)
    - Kinney Building (2 of 3), 1912-1931 (Offsite-box CG-209, Volume 73-78)
    - Kinney Building (3 of 3), 1912-1931 (Offsite-box CG-210, Volume 79-81)
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1 of 2), 1901-1916 (Offsite-box CG-210, Volume 82-83)
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition (2 of 2), 1901-1916 (Offsite-box CG-211, Volume 84)
    - Minnesota State Capital (1 of 4), 1902-1907 (Offsite-box CG-211, Volume 85-89)
    - Minnesota State Capital (2 of 4), 1902-1907 (Offsite-box CG-212, Volume 90-95)
    - Minnesota State Capital (3 of 4), 1902-1907 (Offsite-box CG-213, Volume 96-99)
    - Minnesota State Capital (4 of 4), 1902-1907 (Offsite-box CG-214, Volume 100-103)
    - Montana Club, 1904-1905 (Offsite-box CG-214, Volume 104)
    - National State Savings Bank, 1910-1915 (Offsite-box CG-215, Volume 105-107)
    - New York County Lawyer's Association, 1929 (Offsite-box CG-215, Volume 108-110)
    - New York Life Insurance Building (1 of 4), 1924-1936 (Offsite-box CG-216, Volume 111-116)
    - New York Life Insurance Building (2 of 4), 1924-1936 (Offsite-box CG-217, Volume 117-121)
    - New York Life Insurance Building (3 of 4), 1924-1936 (Offsite-box CG-218, Volume 122-124)
    - New York Life Insurance Building (4 of 4), 1924-1936 (Offsite-box CG-219, Volume 125)
    - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Stations- Bartow Station, 1910-1918 (Offsite-box CG-219, Volume 126)
    - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Stations- New Haven Station, 1917-1919 (Offsite-box CG-219, Volume 127-129)
    - Oberlin College (1 of 3), 1905-1930 (Offsite-box CG-220, Volume 130-135)
    - Oberlin College (2 of 3), 1905-1930 (Offsite-box CG-221, Volume 136-140)
    - Oberlin College (3 of 3), 1905-1930 (Offsite-box CG-222, Volume 141-143)
    - 130 West 30th Street, 1927-1929 (Offsite-box CG-222, Volume 144)
    - Prudential Life Insurance Company Bridges and Buildings (1 of 3), 1925-1934 (Offsite-box CG-223, Volume 145-151)
    - Prudential Life Insurance Company Bridges and Buildings (2 of 3), 1925-1934 (Offsite-box CG-224, Volume 152-158)
    - Prudential Life Insurance Company Bridges and Buildings (3 of 3), 1925-1934 (Offsite-box CG-225, Volume 159-161)
    - Rodin Studios (1 of 2), 1916-1918 (Offsite-box CG-225, Volume 162)
    - Rodin Studios (2 of 2), 1916-1918 (Offsite-box CG-226, Volume 163-165)
    - Sailor's Snug Harbor Apartments, 1922 (Offsite-box CG-226, Volume 166)
    - Saint Louis First National Bank, 1919-1921 (Offsite-box CG-226, Volume 167)
    - Saint Louis Hotel, 1908-1909 (Offsite-box CG-227, Volume 168)
    - Saint Louis Public Library (1 of 3), 1907-1916 (Offsite-box CG-227, Volume 169-173)
    - Saint Louis Public Library (2 of 3), 1907-1916 (Offsite-box CG-228, Volume 174-177)
    - Saint Louis Public Library (3 of 3), 1907-1916 (Offsite-box CG-229, Volume 178)
    - Saint Peter's Hospital, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box CG-229, Volume 179)
    - Scheuer Building, 1904-1906 (Offsite-box CG-229, Volume 180)
    - School of Industrial Arts (1 of 2), 1909-1910 (Offsite-box CG-229, Volume 181-182)
    - School of Industrial Arts (2 of 2), 1909-1910 (Offsite-box CG-230, Volume 183)
    - Scott Fountain and Belle Isle Bridge (1 of 2), 1914-1932 (Offsite-box CG-230, Volume 184-187)
    - Scott Fountain and Belle Isle Bridge (2 of 2), 1914-1932 (Offsite-box CG-231, Volume 188)
    - Scoville Manufacturing Company, 1917-1920 (Offsite-box CG-231, Volume 189)
    - Seaside Sanatorium (1 of 4), 1931-1935 (Offsite-box CG-231, Volume 190-195)
    - Seaside Sanatorium (2 of 4), 1931-1935 (Offsite-box CG-232, Volume 196-200)
    - Seaside Sanatorium ( 3 of 4), 1931-1935 (Offsite-box CG-233, Volume 201-205)
    - Seaside Sanatorium (4 of 4), 1931-1935 (Offsite-box CG-234, Volume 206)
    - Spaulding Building, 1909-1916 (Offsite-box CG-234, Volume 207-208)
    - Union Central Life Insurance Building (1 of 2), 1911-1913 (Offsite-box CG-234, Volume 209-211)
    - Union Central Life Insurance Building (2 of 2), 1911-1913 (Offsite-box CG-235, Volume 212-215)
    - Union Club (1 of 2), 1900-1914 (Offsite-box CG-236, Volume 216-222)
    - Union Club (2 of 2), 1900-1914 (Offsite-box CG-237, Volume 223)
    - United States Army Supply Base, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box CG-237, Volume 224-226)
    - United States Chamber of Commerce (1 of 3), 1919-1925 (Offsite-box CG-237, Volume 227-228)
    - United States Chamber of Commerce (3 of 3), 1919-1925 (Offsite-box CG-239, Volume 234)
    - United States Chamber of Commerce (2 of 3), 1919-1925 (Offsite-box CG-238, Volume 229-233)
    - United States Court House, 1932 (Offsite-box CG-239, Volume 235)
    - United States Custom House (1 of 4), 1899-1921 (Offsite-box CG-239, Volume 236-238)
    - United States Custom House (2 of 4), 1899-1921 (Offsite-box CG-240, Volume 239-244)
    - United States Custom House (3 of 4), 1899-1921 (Offsite-box CG-241, Volume 245-250)
    - United States Custom House (4 of 4), 1899-1921 (Offsite-box CG-242, Volume 251-255)
    - United States Legation Building (1 of 2), 1926-1932 (Offsite-box CG-242, Volume 256)
    - United States Legation Building (2 of 2), 1926-1932 (Offsite-box CG-243, Volume 257)
    - United States Supreme Court Building (1 of 2), 1921-1938 (Offsite-box CG-243, Volume 258-262)
    - United States Supreme Court Building (2 of 2), 1921-1938 (Offsite-box CG-244, Volume 263-269)
    - United States Treasury Department Annex, 1918-1921 (Offsite-box CG-245, Volume 270-272)
    - University of Minnesota, 1909-1911 (Offsite-box CG-245, Volume 273)
    - University of Texas (1 of 2), 1910-1922 (Offsite-box CG-245, Volume 274-275)
    - University of Texas (2 of 2), 1910-1922 (Offsite-box CG-246, Volume 276-277)
    - Waterbury Club, 1917-1918 (Offsite-box CG-246, Volume 278)
    - Waterbury Municipal Building (1 of 2), 1914-1921 (Offsite-box CG-246, Volume 279)
    - Waterbury Municipal Building (2 of 2), 1914-1921 (Offsite-box CG-247, Volume 280-284)
    - Waterbury National Bank (1 of 2), 1919-1922 (Offsite-box CG-248, Volume 285-289)
    - Waterbury National Bank (2 of 2), 1919-1922 (Offsite-box CG-249, Volume 290-291)
    - West Street Building, 1906-1909 (Offsite-box CG-249, Volume 292-294)
    - West Virginia State Capitol (1 of 3), 1921-1931 (Offsite-box CG-250, Volume 295-300)
    - West Virginia State Capitol (2 of 3), 1921-1931 (Offsite-box CG-251, Volume 301-305)
    - West Virginia State Capitol (3 of 3), 1921-1931 (Offsite-box CG-252, Volume 306)
    - Williams Warehouse, 1927-1928 (Offsite-box CG-252, Volume 307-308)
    - Wisconsin State Capitol, 1905-1907 (Offsite-box CG-253, Volume 309)
    - Woolworth Building (1 of 4), 1910-1913 (Offsite-box CG-253, Volume 310-313)
    - Woolworth Building (2 of 4), 1910-1913 (Offsite-box CG-254, Volume 314-316)
    - Woolworth Building (3 of 4), 1910-1913 (Offsite-box CG-255, Volume 317-320)
    - Woolworth Building (4 of 4), 1910-1913 (Offsite-box CG-256, Volume 321-322)
    - Woolworth Memorial Church, 1912-1915 (Offsite-box CG-256, Volume 323)
    - Various Projects (1 of 4), 1892-1925 (Offsite-box CG-256, Volume 324-326)
    - Various Projects (2 of 4), 1892-1925 (Offsite-box CG-257, Volume 327-332)
    - Various Projects (3 of 4), 1892-1925 (Offsite-box CG-258, Volume 333-339)
    - Various Projects (4 of 4), 1892-1925 (Offsite-box CG-259, Volume 340-342)
  - Subseries III: Oversize Material
    The oversize material includes loose items as well as bound scrapbooks relating to Cass Gilbert's projects. The material consists of photographs, drawings and books of newspaper clippings.
    - Charleston Public Library- Drawings, 1906 (Offsite-box 681)
    - Kill Van Kull Bridge- Drawings, 1928 (Offsite-box 681)
    - National State Bank- Photographs, Undated (Offsite-box 681)
    - Minnesota State Capitol- Photographs, 1897-1903 (Offsite-box 681)
    - United States Custom House- Photographs of Interior and Exterior, 1907 (Offsite-box 681)
    - University of Minnesota- Photographs, 1909 (Offsite-box 681)
    - Woolworth Building- Photographs and Drawings, 1911 (Offsite-box 681, Folder 15)
    - Austin Nichols Building (Offsite-box 681, Folder 16)
      Scope and Contents
      photograph of the interior of an office at Austin Nichols and Co., donated by the grandaughter of William S. Watson, who worked at Austin Nichols for 47 years. The man in glasses appears to be Cass Gilbert.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Paula Watson Elliott, 2007.
    - Unidentified Bridges and Buildings, Undated (Offsite-box 681, Folder 17)
    - Woolworth Building, Dinner Given in Honor of Cass Gilbert by Mr. Woolworth - Photograph (2 copies), 1913 (Box PR52)
      Location note
      There are two copies of this photograph, both held in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections, in PR52, Portrait File, Group Portraits (Flat files, Large), Commercial Activities. These photographs are not part of the original collection and were donated separately.
    - Minnesota State Capitol- Newspaper Clippings Book, 1903-1905 (Offsite-box 682)
    - West Virginia State Capitol- Clippings Book, 1920-1925 (Offsite-box 683)
    - United States Supreme Court Building- Photographs of Building Models and Cabinet Sketches, 1931 (Offsite-box 684)
- Series II. Office Files
  This series includes all administrative files relating to Gilbert's professional career and the running of his office. This includes information on his employees, the products and services used by the office, and the different office spaces inhabited by the architecture firm. The office files also document Gilbert's outside professional work such as serving as a judge for architecture competitions, advising on city planning, and his opposition to a plan to build a power plant in Washington D.C. Most of the files are designated #103.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence
    The office correspondence is mostly incoming and any significant amounts of outgoing copies are filed separately. The letters are filed by date and then by correspondent. The general office correspondence consists of letters regarding potential projects, businesses promoting their products, and orders for supplies. Correspondence regarding workers consists of letters of introduction, men's letters asking for work, and a set of letters from office employees who want recommendations to serve in World War I. The correspondence also includes professional matters such as asking Cass Gilbert to speak at events or to judge architecture competitions. This subseries includes letters from Cass Gilbert Jr. if they relate to the business. Personal letters from Cass Gilbert, Jr. can be found in Series IV.
    - Office Correspondence, Undated, 1892-1900 (Offsite-box 566)
    - Office Correspondence, 1900-1902 (Offsite-box 567)
    - Office Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Offsite-box 568)
    - Office Correspondence, 1903-1905 (Offsite-box 569)
    - Office Correspondence, 1906-1907 (Offsite-box 570)
    - Office Correspondence, 1907-1908 (Offsite-box 571)
    - Office Correspondence, 1908-1909 (Offsite-box 572)
    - Office Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 573)
    - Office Correspondence, 1911 (Offsite-box 574)
    - Office Correspondence, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 575)
    - Office Correspondence, 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 576)
    - Office Correspondence, 1913-1914 (Offsite-box 577)
    - Office Correspondence, 1914-1915 (Offsite-box 578)
    - Office Correspondence, 1915 (Offsite-box 579)
    - Office Correspondence, 1916 (Offsite-box 580)
    - Office Correspondence, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box 581)
    - Office Correspondence, 1917-1918 (Offsite-box 582)
    - Office Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box 583)
    - Office Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Offsite-box 584)
    - Office Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Offsite-box 585)
    - Office Correspondence, 1921-1922 (Offsite-box 586)
    - Office Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 587)
    - Office Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Offsite-box 588)
    - Office Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Offsite-box 589)
    - Office Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Offsite-box 590)
    - Office Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Offsite-box 591)
    - Office Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Offsite-box 592)
    - Office Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Offsite-box 593)
    - Office Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Offsite-box 594)
    - Office Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 595)
    - Office Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Offsite-box 596)
    - Office Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Offsite-box 597)
    - Office Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Offsite-box 598)
    - Office Correspondence, 1934 (Offsite-box 599)
  - Subseries II: Memoranda
    This subseries contains memoranda regarding office procedures, office spaces, the documentation of phone calls, and the discussion of possible projects.
    - Memoranda (Box 1 of 2), 1900-1934 (Offsite-box 599)
    - Memoranda (Box 2 of 2), 1900-1934 (Offsite-box 600)
  - Subseries III: Reports
    The reports in this subseries relate to Gilbert's office, business, or planning strategies for New York City and Washington, DC.
    - Reports (Box 1 of 2), 1923-1932 (Offsite-box 600)
    - Reports (Box 2 of 2), 1923-1932 (Offsite-box 601)
  - Subseries IV: Contracts/Agreements
    This subseries contains contracts and agreements for services and office space.
    - Contracts, Undated, 1904-1916 (Offsite-box 601)
    - Agreements for Office Space, 1901-1935 (Offsite-box 601)
  - Subseries V.: Financial Documents
    The financial documents relate to employee payments, rents for office space, and payments for general goods and services.
    - Payroll Records (Box 1 of 4), 1912-1928 (Offsite-box 601)
    - Payroll Records (Box 2 of 4), 1912-1928 (Offsite-box 602)
    - Payroll Records (Box 3 of 4), 1912-1928 (Offsite-box 603)
    - Payroll Records (Box 4 of 4), 1912-1928 (Offsite-box 604)
    - Distribution and Notes re Salaries, 1912-1931 (Offsite-box 604)
    - Bills and Receipts (Box 1 of 2), 1899-1933 (Offsite-box 604)
    - Bills and Receipts (Box 2 of 2), 1899-1933 (Offsite-box 605)
    - Vouchers (Box 1 of 2), 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 605)
    - Vouchers (Box 2 of 2), 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 606)
    - Petty Cash Accounts, 1900-1908 (Offsite-box 606)
    - Payments for Office Space, 1902-1906 (Offsite-box 606)
  - Subseries VI: Calendars
    This subseries includes weekly calendars with space for a daily agenda. The calendars document his meetings, travel plans, and what he completed in the office for a particular day.
    - Weekly Appointment Calendars (Box 1 of 2), 1914-1934 (Offsite-box 607)
    - Weekly Appointment Calendars (Box 2 of 2), 1914-1934 (Offsite-box 608)
  - Subseries VII: Publications
    This subseries includes offers from various magazines for the publication of plans or for subscriptions to the magazine.
    - Various Publications, 1900-1907 (Offsite-box 608)
  - Subseries VIII: Clippings
    The clippings in this subseries include articles related to the architectural projects of Gilbert's office or by other architects. The subseries also contains clippings regarding the proposed power plant in Washington D.C. and city plans for New York City.
    - Clippings, 1901-1931 (Offsite-box 608)
  - Subseries IX: Other Material
    This subseries contains other office and professional files. It includes documents regarding the NYC Regional Plan, the Washington DC Power Plant Site, office spaces, office policies, employees, John Rockart vs. Cass Gilbert Inc., etc.
    - Miscellaneous Office Files (Box 1 of 2), 1900-1937 (Offsite-box 609)
    - Miscellaneous Office Files (Box 2 of 2), 1900-1937 (Offsite-box 610)
  - Subseries X: Bound Volumes
    Most of the volumes are letterbooks that contain copies of outgoing letters from Gilbert's office. Other volumes include contract records, cash books, journals of expenses, records of work, payroll ledgers, and a transcript from James Stewart & Co. vs. US Claims Court. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
    - Letterbooks (1 of 5), 1883-1937 (Offsite-box CG-259, Volume 343-346)
    - Letterbooks (2 of 5), 1883-1937 (Offsite-box CG-260, Volume 347-352)
    - Letterbooks (3 of 5), 1883-1937 (Offsite-box CG-261, Volume 353-358)
    - Letterbooks (4 of 5), 1883-1937 (Offsite-box CG-262, Volume 359-364)
    - Letterbooks (5 of 5), 1883-1937 (Offsite-box CG-263, Volume 365-371)
    - Contract Records, 1909-1937 (Offsite-box CG-264, Volume 372)
    - Cash Books (1 of 2), 1883-1934 (Offsite-box CG-264, Volume 373-377)
    - Cash Books (2 of 2), 1883-1934 (Offsite-box CG-265, Volume 378-380)
    - Journals of Expenses, 1903-1934 (Offsite-box CG-265, Volume 381-383)
    - Records of Work, 1891-1908 (Offsite-box CG-266, Volume 384-385)
    - Payroll Ledger, 1928-1935 (Offsite-box CG-266, Volume 386)
    - Cass Gilbert Jr. Testimony for the Plaintiff in James Stewart & Co. vs. US Claims Court, Volume I, 1942 (Offsite-box CG-266, Volume 387)
  - Subseries XI: Oversize Materials
    The oversize materials include a brochure on the Hollar Company, a copy of Skyscrapers of New York by Vernon Howe Bailey, service sheets by the Architectural Service Corporation, and a photograph of the artists at the Columbian Exposition Building.
    - Brochure on Hollar Company, [1920] (Offsite-box 685)
    - Skyscrapers of New York by Vernon Howe Bailey with introduction by Cass Gilbert, 1923 (Offsite-box 685)
    - Service Sheets by the Architectural Service Corporation, 1916-1919 (Offsite-box 685)
- Series III. Professional Organizations
  This series includes documents relating to Cass Gilbert's involvement in art and architectural organizations. Files relating to his participation in other organizations or causes are located within his personal files. The organizations most heavily represented are the American Institute of Architects, the Commission of Fine Arts, and the National Academy of Design.
  - Subseries I. Foldered Material:
    Most of the subseries consists of correspondence but memoranda, reports and brochures are also included. The files regarding the American Institute of Architects include materials on the national organization as well as the state and local chapters. The files also include correspondence regarding his resignation from the AIA.
    - Alpha Rho Chi, 1924-1934 (Offsite-box 610)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box 1 of 2), 1915-1934 (Offsite-box 610)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box 2 of 2), 1915-1934 (Offsite-box 611)
    - American Academy in Rome (Box 1 of 2), 1905-1925 (Offsite-box 611)
    - American Academy in Rome (Box 2 of 2), 1905-1925 (Offsite-box 612)
    - American Artists' Committee of One Hundred, 1916-1922 (Offsite-box 612)
    - American Federation of Arts (Box 1 of 2), 1910-1934 (Offsite-box 612)
    - American Federation of Arts (Box 2 of 2), 1910-1934 (Offsite-box 613)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 1 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 613)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 2 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 614)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 3 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 615)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 4 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 616)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 5 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 617)
    - American Institute of Architects (Box 6 of 7), 1901-1936 (Offsite-box 618)